<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-06T21:34:40+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Homepage of Pascal Brokmeier</title><subtitle>Check out my about page for more, read my blog or watch me code on YouTube or just take a picture of mine for your wallpaper. I share everything for free and really enjoy good conversations about meaningful topics. Let me know if you have something to talk about.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Visiting the #HambiBleibt demonstration</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/09/10/Visiting_the_HambiBleibt_demonstration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting the #HambiBleibt demonstration" /><published>2018-09-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/09/10/Visiting_the_HambiBleibt_demonstration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/09/10/Visiting_the_HambiBleibt_demonstration.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I visited the demonstrations against RWEs large lignite (aka brown coal) factory and their plans to cut down
the last parts of a formerly huge forest. It’s close to my home and I decided to see for myself what so many people are
so passionate about. This is my report of my observed behavior, my talks to people and the conclusions I drew from the
day. If you just want to look at some nice pics, check the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick summary for those that don’t live here or know much about coal mining:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lignite&quot;&gt;Lignite&lt;/a&gt; is a low rank fossil fuel energy source that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lignite#Production&quot;&gt;most widely
used&lt;/a&gt; in Germany. RWE, one of the large energy providers here runs
several large surface mines to retrieve the lignite. They cover a surface area of about the same surface as the
metropolitan area of Cologne. Standing on the edge of these giant holes is severely impressive. Aside from the obvious
issues of fossil fuels, the reasons for the demonstrations are the fact that surface mines need to destroy large surface
areas to retrieve the underlying fuel. This includes removing entire villages, forcing people out of their homes as well
as clearing forests and thereby destroying large CO2 capturing vegetation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, modern society needs a consistent energy source and while renewable energy is discussed as the future
of energy, it cannot provide when outside conditions (such as solar intensity, wind speeds and water throughput) are not
sufficient. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542435118303866?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;great article&lt;/a&gt; (Sepulveda
et.al.) clearly lists the interaction and requirement of all three types of energy infrastructure that is required to
reach low-carbon energy grids. &lt;em&gt;Firm&lt;/em&gt; resources such as coal, gas or nuclear energy are required to complement sporadic,
volatile renewable sources and storage or curtailment technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demonstration is about a small patch of forest, hardly a relevant amount of forest when considering the amounts that
we need to save. But it serves as a signal. A forest on the edge of the coal mine, trees that are to be removed to make
space for machines and coal. That is why activists have defended and sometimes even lived in this forest for several
years now. Technically owned by RWE, there are patches of land that are owned by others and a small, semi-permanent camp
has been created there that supports this demonstration. Within the next weeks, it will have to be decided which side
gets their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;positions-and-observations&quot;&gt;Positions and Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Sunday, I talked to a few people to hear about their experiences and learn about what is going on. I asked the
organizer of the demonstration (organized by “grüne Jugend”) about a case where an activist has been sentenced to jail
for several months &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23freeupiii&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;see tag #freeUPIII&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, not much
was told about this. It appears that this activist must have done &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; wrong but the way she is detained seems
peculiar. Especially for a person that cannot speak German, it must be troubling to be detained and put into prison
without having contact to the outside world. On the other hand I still want to believe that a police force will not just
take someone and throw them into prison for no reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7065.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;6000&quot; height=&quot;4000&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let myself fall back and started talking to the police. I was told they saw attacks with Molotov cocktails and stones
in the past weeks. I assume these attacks must be reported somewhere, especially since the police carries large cameras
on sticks during such activities. It would be interesting to see such photographic proof, at least as long as we can
still rely on such proof, since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GRQuRcpf5Gc&quot;&gt;AI may take that away again soon&lt;/a&gt;.
Generally, they spoke about a lot of “violence, originating in the forest” but pointed out the very peaceful climate on
Sunday. There was no comment on the burned bus that was holding materials for the activists which was parked in Buir
which was most likely burned down by someone, unless it (ironically a former fire-truck) suffered spontaneous
self-combustion. An investigation is pending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7070.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;6000&quot; height=&quot;4000&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7071.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;6000&quot; height=&quot;4000&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something else I noticed: when the procession reached the camp on the outskirts of the forest, one face-mask wearing
resident of the camp apparently came too close to the demonstration and the police followed him for a little while. I
guess, when wearing face masks during a demonstration, you walk a fine line (&lt;a href=&quot;https://dejure.org/gesetze/VersG/17a.html&quot;&gt;link to
law&lt;/a&gt;). Once he moved away, they let him go. Another figure has been standing
on the outskirts of the demonstration, watching the whole process from far away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7072.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1918&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official part was over and therefore the police left. I took my bike and walked towards the camp, assuming that
while I don’t look &lt;em&gt;like one of them&lt;/em&gt; I also don’t have to worry to be mistaken with a police officer. The mood in the
camp was quiet and peaceful, people cleaned their dogs fur and talked about organizing water and electricity. I saw a
sign that complained about someone who spent a night in the “info-point”, because that person apparently didn’t behave
and left everything in a mess. The clay based self-built houses and old camper vans made a cute street of random
buildings. I definitely respect the creativity and ability to whip up a local power grid with a few solar panels and a
small wind mill. There seemed to be no water supply however. I noticed the people there weren’t quiet as talkative as
the police officers which was curious to me. I guess I overdid the whole &lt;em&gt;look like a business student&lt;/em&gt; approach, which
was supposed to get me past any potential filter points that I read about the previous days. The overall vibe was
definitely that of a lingering conflict that is all about tactics, making the right moves and collecting information. I
took my bike through the actual forest which was covered with small pieces of wood and some larger structures such as a
few meter high tripods. Nothing that would actually keep RWE from taking the forest apart of course, but I guess it was
the thought that counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the bike out of the forest after a while, I aimed towards the large machinery at the horizon. From a technical
perspective, these machines are fascinating to me and I wanted to get a better look. I saw a police van on the top of
the hill and figured they’d be nice and friendly, as we are not in the US and I haven’t attacked anyone. I arrived and
the mood was in fact nice and friendly, although they assumed I was “from the camp” as I later overheard the leading
officer mumble to a pair of undercover patrols that stopped by. In that moment I corrected him and realized that I
wanted to be neither associated with the people in the camp nor with the company. I was an observer and apparently that
was important enough to me that I spoke up right away. He noted that he just wanted to ensure that the colleagues don’t
spill any internal information while I am around. That of course is a clear signal that there is a form of tactical
forth and back going on. The police have plans that are best kept secret and so do the camp inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I took my bike back around the forest and headed towards Buir. Just before the city, I stopped at the
Greenpeace truck and talked to some people there. It seemed that everyone is aware of the complexity of this problem:
kill coal and atomic energy and you loose a solid network. of this problem: kill coal and atomic energy and you loose a
solid network. of this problem: kill coal and atomic energy and you loose a solid network. of this problem: kill coal
and atomic energy and you loose a solid network. of this problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kill coal and atomic energy and you loose the stability in the network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kill too many trees and you loose all the CO2 regulating nature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build too many Lithium batteries to store energy and you kill the climate through the up-front costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electric cars may make the problem better (as storage utilities) or worse (through more electricity demand)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;solutions cannot come from simply one of the three components (cultural change, tech and regulation/market design) but
  through a combination&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;questionable police actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extremists within the ranks of the activists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;political lethargy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lobby influence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a nice talk and although we just kept uncovering more and more reasons for why the problem is complex, I wish
such talks, also between both opposing fronts, were more common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7075.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;6016&quot; height=&quot;4016&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is any conclusion to draw it is that there are a large number of problems at play. As a mathematician, one may
say there is no global optima. If thousands of stakeholders all weigh there criteria in different ways, how is one to
derive a solution that satisfies everyone without triggering anyone to feel so unfairly treated that they are willing to
trigger violence. Some see themselves as the guardians of nature while others see themselves as the hated few that make
everyone’s coffee maker work in the morning. Narratives that we tell ourselves to justify why we do the things we do I
guess. I believe these situations are very intense for a lot of people, including the police and many activists and RWE
employees but that doesn’t mean they are warranted. If the game was designed in a way that lignite wasn’t economically
feasible anymore, it wouldn’t be mined anymore. So shouldn’t the most effective lever really be in the area of policy
design and market design? I believe we need elegant market designs that make market participants &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to save energy,
use it intelligently, produce it sustainably and be fine some compromises. Me personally, I will dig deeper into the
research of how the markets work and figure out what wrong incentives might be given to corporations like RWE that cause
them to behave in such a crude fashion of just uprooting whatever is in the way to dig up some more of this really dirty
energy source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final image, I found the solar panels on the outskirts of Buir fascinating. About a kilometer of large packs of
solar panels, all angled towards the sun. Ironically, the same company that digs up all this coal is the one that places
the panels all over the hills. But its again theirs, and if solar panels end up being an evil technology, they surely
would defend them just as they defend the coal today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-09-10/DSC_7058.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;6016&quot; height=&quot;4016&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="hambacher,forst,forest,coal,energy,renewable,demonstration" /><summary type="html">I visited the demonstrations against the RWE coal mine nearby Cologne and talked to some participants to see first hand how the story is seen from the people that are involved.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My XPS customizing diary</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/08/11/My_XPS_customizing_diary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My XPS customizing diary" /><published>2018-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/08/11/My_XPS_customizing_diary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/08/11/My_XPS_customizing_diary.html">&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of 2018 I started looking for a laptop that would serve as my mobile workstation. I bike a lot so there
is a weight restriction to it. After a lengthy research phase where I compared the Thinkpads, Huawei Matebooks and some
other competitors, I ended up choosing the XPS 15. It was discounted and I also made use of the student discount so I ended up
paying about 1050€ for it. It’s the 16GB, 512GB SSD, i7 7700k 1080p 96Wh variant. Most importantly it is the US keyboard
layout variant. You wouldn’t believe how hard it is to get a US keyboard on a laptop in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article serves as a summary about what I have done to make this machine my machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12-14h battery life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;manjaro OS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i3 window manager with rofi, conky, polybar, …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new intel wifi card for BT 5.0 and best performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ipad as secondary monitor via vnc and x11vnc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;see video at the bottom for a lazy variant of inspiration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;battery-life-story&quot;&gt;Battery life story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-term-health&quot;&gt;Long term health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to make the most out of the battery you got. Dell offers some nice settings in the BIOS that allow
you to limit the battery to some value. I set this to 90% because this device is already offering such great battery
life. This way, my battery never charges more than 90% which greatly helps to keep it healthy for long. Check your
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/sys/devices/LNXSYSTM:00/LNXSYBUS:00/PNP0C0A:00/power_supply/BAT0&lt;/code&gt; path for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# 1: full, 2: full_design, 3: now
[pascalwhoop-xps BAT0]# cat charge*
7670000
8509000
3552000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-term-durability&quot;&gt;Short term durability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, it’s configured so I will be happy for a few hundred cycles. But you also want to make it through the day. Four key factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display brightness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPU usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fan usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Idle usage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;display-brightness&quot;&gt;Display brightness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the display: I set mine to 30-50% most of the time. It’s the core component to making the device last
during day to day use. These settings are enough for indoors and I use dark themes which
work well with low display brightness settings. But these themes are aweful to read when it’s bright, which is often the
case outdoors or when you’re on a train / plane. So for this I have a few tools to quickly change my GTK3 theme as well
as my terminal theme. This permits readability in bright environments where black on white is better to read than white
on black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sos4nt/dynamic-colors/&quot;&gt;dynamic colors&lt;/a&gt; let’s you quickly change the urxvt themes. Good, but it
  doesn’t change &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the terminal windows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/dotfiles/blob/xps/.scripts/urxvt-colors.py&quot;&gt;this script&lt;/a&gt; changes them for all open
  terminals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to change my entire theme, I run &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/dotfiles/blob/xps/.scripts/colors.sh&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; which
  changes the colors of the shells, makes it permanent for the current session and sets the GTK theme for GTK
  applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/darklight.gif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/darklight.gif 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/darklight.gif 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_900/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/darklight.gif 900w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;506&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s OK to have the brightness low inside and also being able to quickly switch to a bright theme on the road. When
using other tools, the scripts may be extended to incorporate JetBrains tools etc to direkt them to change their themes.
I may add that in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gpu-usage&quot;&gt;GPU Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPU is power hungry! Disable it with bumblebee and only use it when needed using bbswitch. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dell_XPS_15_9560#Disable_discrete_GPU&quot;&gt;arch
wiki&lt;/a&gt; for details. To make it even easier,
try the great &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mhwd&lt;/code&gt; tool that configures the hardware components in your manjaro distro for you. It quickly installs
bumblebee and lets you switch between open source and closed source drivers. I also installed the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cuda&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cudnn&lt;/code&gt;
packages with pacman to do some machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[pascalwhoop@XPS] ~ $ nvidia-smi
NVIDIA-SMI has failed because it couldn't communicate with the NVIDIA driver. Make sure that the latest NVIDIA driver is installed and running.

[pascalwhoop@XPS] ~ $ optirun nvidia-smi
Tue Sep  4 11:10:14 2018
+-----------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| NVIDIA-SMI 396.51                 Driver Version: 396.51                    |
|-------------------------------+----------------------+----------------------+
| GPU  Name        Persistence-M| Bus-Id        Disp.A | Volatile Uncorr. ECC |
| Fan  Temp  Perf  Pwr:Usage/Cap|         Memory-Usage | GPU-Util  Compute M. |
|===============================+======================+======================|
|   0  GeForce GTX 1050    Off  | 00000000:01:00.0 Off |                  N/A |
| N/A   44C    P3    N/A /  N/A |      5MiB /  4042MiB |      0%      Default |
+-------------------------------+----------------------+----------------------+

+-----------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Processes:                                                       GPU Memory |
|  GPU       PID   Type   Process name                             Usage      |
|=============================================================================|
|    0     25064      G   /usr/lib/Xorg                                  5MiB |
+-----------------------------------------------------------------------------+
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, when using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;optirun&lt;/code&gt; tool, your application is run using the GPU but when not using it, everything
stays on the CPU and its integrated Intel graphics. This is really neat for software development work that sometimes
uses the GPU as a co-processor for heavy parallel workloads (like NN) but otherwise has no use for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;media-keys&quot;&gt;(Media) keys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am using i3. So these are my solutions to audio / lights / … function keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#in the i3 config
#media keys
bindsym XF86AudioRaiseVolume       exec --no-startup-id pactl     set-sink-volume @DEFAULT_SINK@ +10%
bindsym XF86AudioLowerVolume       exec --no-startup-id pactl     set-sink-volume @DEFAULT_SINK@ -10%
bindsym XF86AudioMute              exec --no-startup-id pactl     set-sink-mute   @DEFAULT_SINK@ toggle
bindsym XF86AudioPlay              exec --no-startup-id playerctl play-pause
bindsym XF86AudioPrev              exec --no-startup-id playerctl previous
bindsym XF86AudioNext              exec --no-startup-id playerctl next
bindsym XF86MonBrightnessDown      exec xbacklight      -dec      5
bindsym XF86MonBrightnessUp        exec xbacklight      -inc      10
bindsym $mod+XF86MonBrightnessDown exec xbacklight      -set      1
bindsym $mod+XF86MonBrightnessUp   exec xbacklight      -set      100
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to download &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pactl&lt;/code&gt; for audio control, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;playerctl&lt;/code&gt; for mpd and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mpdris2&lt;/code&gt; for letting playerctl control manage mpd. 
It’s a bit tedious to do this by hand instead of having a desktop environment take care of all of this for you. But the
upside is that you learn about D-BUS as well as how the inside components of your desktop environment work. That’s
definitely a plus. Other players usually support the D-BUS signals out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the other keys: The windows key is my i3 modifier, Caps Lock is my escape + ctrl button&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Map the caps lock key to super...
setxkbmap -layout &quot;us,de&quot; -variant &quot;,&quot; -option ctrl:nocaps
# But when it is pressed only once, treat it as escape.
xcape -e 'Control_L=Escape'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now these keys define a set of my core shortcuts where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod == Win&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+q             kill&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+Ctrl+4        exec    teiler&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+Shift+p       exec    passmenu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+Mod1+space    exec    dmenu_extended_run&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+d             exec    rofi -show combi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$mod+control+space exec    ~/.config/clipmenu/run.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gestures&quot;&gt;Gestures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come from a Macbook. So gestures were really nice there. I experimented quiet a bit with different drivers for the
touchpad but in the end I stuck with the following setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;libinput for the driver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Section &quot;InputClass&quot;
    Identifier &quot;touchpad catchall&quot;
    Driver &quot;libinput&quot;
    MatchIsTouchpad &quot;on&quot;
    Option &quot;Tapping&quot; &quot;on&quot;
    Option &quot;ClickMethod&quot; &quot;clickfinger&quot;
    Option &quot;NaturalScrolling&quot; &quot;true&quot;
    Option &quot;VertTwoFingerScroll&quot; &quot;1&quot;
    Option &quot;AccelSpeed&quot; &quot;0.5&quot;
EndSection
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and libinput-gestures as the gesture tool&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Move to prev workspace (works for GNOME/KDE/etc on Wayland and Xorg)
gesture swipe down  _internal ws_down
# gesture swipe down    xdotool key super+Page_Up

# Browser go forward (works only for Xorg, and Xwayland clients)
gesture swipe left 3    xdotool key &quot;ctrl+35&quot;
gesture swipe left 4    i3 workspace next

# Browser go back (works only for Xorg, and Xwayland clients)
gesture swipe right 3   xdotool key &quot;ctrl+34&quot;
gesture swipe right 4   i3 workspace prev
gesture swipe up 4 xdotool key &quot;Super_L+f&quot;
gesture swipe down 4 xdotool key &quot;Super_L+f&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These gestures allow me to switch between the i3 spaces and also let me use the three finger forward/backward in the
browser for navigation. The latter is most important to me as browsing really involves a lot of touchpad usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;virtual-machines&quot;&gt;Virtual machines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with VMWare Player and VirtualBox in the past but then got a recommendation to try &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;libvirt&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;virt-manager&lt;/code&gt; which I then installed and configured as described in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Libvirt&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lets me start and stop my VM’s using commands in my i3 config, similar to my other starting scripts. I haven’t
mapped anything yet because I almost never use a VM on my laptop but it is nice to know that I can map it to a quick
keyboard shortcut instead of opening an application and then clicking around. Also, this let’s me always start my VM on
full-screen in space 6 (my VM space) and it’s also interesting to learn the open source components of the Linux VM
landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ui-customizations&quot;&gt;UI Customizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i3 by default is rather ugly (*personal opinion). So I used&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i3-gaps&lt;/code&gt; to make it look a bit more sleek&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;polybar&lt;/code&gt; instead of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i3-bar&lt;/code&gt; for media, system stats, spaces indicators and tray icons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rofi&lt;/code&gt; as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dmenu&lt;/code&gt; replacement for a number of tools such as
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;clipmenu&lt;/code&gt; for a clipboard history that synchronizes across my machines via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;syncthing&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rofi&lt;/code&gt; itself to start applications and jump to running windows between spaces&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dmenu-extended&lt;/code&gt; using the rofi interface to search my files (based on the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mlocate&lt;/code&gt; tool)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Arc-Dark&lt;/code&gt; GTK theme to style everything in a nice and uniform way
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adapting the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;conky&lt;/code&gt; bar on my right side and the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;polybar&lt;/code&gt; themes to use the same colors as Arc-Dark&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/dotfiles/blob/xps/.scripts/colors.sh&quot;&gt;custom script&lt;/a&gt; to switch between  &lt;em&gt;dark&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;light&lt;/em&gt; environments
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;switches between Arc-Dark and Arc-Light, including all terminals and GTK applications (after a restart of the gtk
  apps)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is the result of all of this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;distraction free&lt;/em&gt; writing environment using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Goyo&lt;/code&gt; in vim combined with a full-screen terminal and some transparency
settings using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;compton&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/1.png 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2 side split pane for two side by side applications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/2.png 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using rofi to switch between open windows or open new applications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/3.png 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite: transparent terminals help to work with a small screen when looking up something on stackoverflow and
typing it into the terminal afterwards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/4.png 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;locking-on-lid-close-or-button-press&quot;&gt;Locking on lid close or button press&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want my laptop to lock the screen and suspend to RAM when closing the lid. I also like to just hit the power button to
lock the device quickly in case I walk away. For this, I had to first disable &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt; handling of the ACPI events and
then activate and configure &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acpid&lt;/code&gt; under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/etc/acpid/handler.sh&lt;/code&gt;. So first I disabled systemd as &lt;a href=&quot;https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/52645&quot;&gt;described
here&lt;/a&gt;. Then I set my &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;handler.sh&lt;/code&gt; to call &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i3lock -c 222222&lt;/code&gt; on pressing my
power button and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i3exit suspend&lt;/code&gt; when closing the lid. I know that this is a little unintelligent because it links my
acpi event to my WM. But I am happy with it for now. I could alternatively rely on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;slock&lt;/code&gt; and call &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;systemctl suspend&lt;/code&gt;
but I like the look of the blurred i3exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-08-11/5.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;844&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;others&quot;&gt;Others&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/dotfiles/tree/xps&quot;&gt;My dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; host most of my configs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hub.docker.com/r/linuxserver/syncthing/&quot;&gt;syncthing&lt;/a&gt; in a docker container takes care of syncing files between
  my devices without touching a cloud. It uses SSL encrypted  P2P torrent protocols to synchronize between devices and
  directly synchronizes between them if they are in the same network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using my iPad as a secondary monitor using a VNC app as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/dotfiles/commit/52be449469f91bfa6a76b94f5fbe223ff665bcb8&quot;&gt;these scripts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;purchasing the intel 9260 wifi card and replacing the killer wifi card. I only noticed issues with one wifi network
  but didn’t want to risk it. Plus, BT5.0 right?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/YMiqNJaqvrk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="xps,laptop,unix,linux,hardware" /><summary type="html">A collection of modifications I did to my XPS to make it my very personal work machine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to get Lightroom running on Linux with WebAssembly and nativefier</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/30/How_to_get_lightroom_running_on_Linux_with_Webassembly_and_Nativefier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get Lightroom running on Linux with WebAssembly and nativefier" /><published>2018-05-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/30/How_to_get_lightroom_running_on_Linux_with_Webassembly_and_Nativefier</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/30/How_to_get_lightroom_running_on_Linux_with_Webassembly_and_Nativefier.html">&lt;p&gt;So… Adobe we need to talk: Your stuff is great, pretty pricy and we all know you’re trying to lock us in, but hey.
Can’t blame you. But! No love for Linux users? Well I’ll help you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adobe released Lightroom for the Web. It’s based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebAssembly&quot;&gt;webassembly&lt;/a&gt; which (if
you don’t know) is pretty awesome stuff. Adobe has Lightroom compiled for the web and it’s available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://lightroom.adobe.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. They also have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://lightroom.adobe.com/news&quot;&gt;news channel&lt;/a&gt; which keeps you
up to date with the latest updates for the web version. If you have a decent internet connection and don’t mind
uploading your images to Adobe servers for editing, then go ahead and give it a shot. But wait. I know you want it as a
destkop application right? So here is a little trick:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Make sure you have NodeJS in a recent version installed and also ensure you have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; in your path. If you don’t know
what that is give &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/en/download/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; a go. Got it? Good. Now run the following in a folder where
you usually store portable apps (I got mine in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/Apps&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install -g nativefier
nativefier -n lightroom-web https://lightroom.adobe.com/ --file-download-options '{&quot;saveAs&quot;: true}'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;now cd into the new folder and run the executable &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lightroom-web&lt;/code&gt;. Log in with your Adobe account and give it a go.
should work right out of the box! Below is a screenshot of me running lightroom to edit a picture inside of my
i3-gaps-wm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1600/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-30/ss.jpg 1600w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Lightroom running on i3&quot; width=&quot;3839&quot; height=&quot;2159&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="photography,linux,lightroom,webassembly,nativefier" /><summary type="html">Lightroom is available online. And it's surprisingly good thanks to recent advancements in web-technologies. I'm showing how to get a pretty good version of Lightroom running on linux.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is PowerTAC?</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/09/What_is_PowerTAC_.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is PowerTAC?" /><published>2018-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/09/What_is_PowerTAC_</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/05/09/What_is_PowerTAC_.html">&lt;p&gt;Energy is a major challenge. We are currently using the futures resources and unless we drastically change our behavior,
the world as we know it will be drastically different in 100 years. In every discussion about the costs of renewables,
a common theme is the argument of economic rationality. Current energy sources are X% more effective where X is usually a
low 2 digit number. But it is often dismissed that without a proper change in our behavior, entire continents need to be
restructured. Bangladesh, a comparatively small Asian country will have 25 million people who will have to adjust their
life by 2050, 2100 can only be extrapolated. Developing countries may leapfrog nation-wide electric grid systems just as
they have done with phone lines, going straight to mobile. But industrialized nations require a heavy adaptation of
their infrastructure which was designed based on concepts from almost 100 years ago. Networks are going to be heavily
distributed, with many suppliers and many consumers being able to store energy and use or release it later. PowerTAC
simulates such a scenario simulating a grid market dynamics of a small city. It simulates 3 core
markets: Tariff, wholesale and balancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-09/powertac_overview.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-09/powertac_overview.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-09/powertac_overview.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-09/powertac_overview.png 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1047/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-05-09/powertac_overview.png 1047w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1047&quot; height=&quot;580&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tariff-market&quot;&gt;Tariff market&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first market simulates the creation and adoption of tariffs in a end-user centered market.Brokers, the main actors
in the simulation, compete for customers by offering tariffs on the market. Customers evaluate these tariffs and choose
one they prefer. They are lazy and suffer limited rationality, just like most normal humans. There are a number of rules
that govern the publishing of tariffs but basically, this market is rather idealistic and allows for many interesting
tariff options. Rates may change prices based on the time of the day or on the usage per day. They may be adaptive,
following the live market price. And they may offer customers to forfeit part of their usage for a strong discount. All
these kinds of options allow a broker to balance its portfolio to allow for a decentralized balancing of the grid load.
If the market prices are high, customers with variable pricing will tend to reduce their usage. If the portfolio is not
balanced, curtailing of customers usage can help recreate an equilibrium. Customers have an incentive to behave
economically and brokers have an incentive to precisely estimate their customers usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wholesale-market&quot;&gt;Wholesale market&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This market allows large actors (such as brokers and large-scale producers / consumers) to trade energy usage rights for
the near future. The simulation offers a 24h horizon, letting brokers bid on each of the upcoming 24 hours. This means
that at any given moment, 24 parallel auctions are performed. This is in line with common market mechanisms and it
allows brokers to buy and sell any excessive or missing energy. Prices are calculated based on the supply and demand
curves just like many known markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;balancing-market&quot;&gt;Balancing market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Balancing market is the last and final trading opportunity for agents and in the sense of the game is at t − 0
meaning that it occurs virtually in parallel to the consummation of energy. Any imbalance during this phase gets
corrected for by the distribution utility (DU) which acts as a final balancer for the market. It imposes forced
balancing of brokers with an imbalanced portfolio. Brokers with too much supply in their portfolio therefore receive
very little reimbursement for it and those whose customers’ usage is higher than the estimated amount pay high prices
for the additionally supplied energy.  Brokers who have tariffs with economic control abilities can pass this capacity
along to the DU who utilizes these capacities to correct the markets imbalances, charging customers’ storage devices if
an oversupply is present or depleting their devices in the case of an under-supply. It is therefore economically
beneficial for brokers to attract customers with such balancing capabilities since it offers a buffer capacity against
the balancing costs otherwise incurred through the actions of the DU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cPUfkg1SPaA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay;
encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-appeal&quot;&gt;The appeal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation is appealing in many regards. It attacks a problem that is both current and significant. It offers the
usage of current state-of-the-art algorithms from machine learning and AI to try and solve these problems. It attempts
to avoid political stupidity by simulating various scenarios before acting them out. While the simulation is currently
not at a scale where it could be seen as a major guide for evaluating arbitrary future market designs, it does offer the
ability to simulate different constructs. Most of all it is a tool game design, offering policy makers and researchers
alike the chance to see how AI driven actors will behave under various game designs in a future energy market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the simulation also has limits. It is currently only available in Java, lacks scalability and requires more
intelligent components. The future will have intelligent agents in hundreds of locations and it should not be limited to
simply simulating broker behavior. Researchers should be able to design intelligent customers, intelligent cars and
household utilities. The market may be based on non-fully-connected grids (such as those often found in developing
worlds), or it may offer a completely peer-to-peer based system based on modern technologies such as block-chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its limitations, the appeal is obvious: Attack the biggest problems of our time with the most sophisticated
algorithms to coordinate various actors in a market-based environment. See how different market designs and different
agent behaviors impact the market and learn before the implementation is complete and changing it would be costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About PowerTAC: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.powertac.org/publications&quot;&gt;http://www.powertac.org/publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Motivation:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://samharris.org/podcasts/what-you-need-to-know-about-climate-change/&quot;&gt;https://samharris.org/podcasts/what-you-need-to-know-about-climate-change/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My GitHub workings: &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/pascalwhoop/&quot;&gt;http://github.com/pascalwhoop/&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;masterthesis&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;grpc-adapter&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;powertac-server&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;broker-python&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="powertac,thesis,energy,software" /><summary type="html">An introduction about the Power Trading Agent Competition in which I am writing my master thesis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dark Side of Youth Mobility</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/04/16/TheDarkSideOfYouthMobility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dark Side of Youth Mobility" /><published>2018-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/04/16/TheDarkSideOfYouthMobility</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/society/2018/04/16/TheDarkSideOfYouthMobility.html">&lt;p&gt;Do you have this friend who always talks about her next city to live in? Or do you know this obnoxious guy who’s living
in your city and is always trash-talking how your city operates? He’s probably from somewhere else and everything is
better somewhere else, which is why he’ll move there after his “finding my true passion” year is finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do, you probably live in a city that I want to put into focus. If you don’t, think twice. You might be the person
that’s painted in bad light here. But you might see yourself in a completely different light: You might call yourself
“Young, mobile, educated, open-minded”. In Europe we call these people the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/news/special-report/21579148-overcome-its-skills-shortage-germany-needs-remodel-its-society-erasmus-generation&quot; title=&quot;Erasmus Generation - The Economist&quot;&gt;Erasmus Generation&lt;/a&gt;” and I am one of them. So
this articles serves as a critical reminder that we are not only a source of goodness but that we might also cause a lot
of unwanted problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here is the sales-pitch: I belong to an extremely mobile generation. I am writing this from my 4th home country,
having volunteered for the Erasmus Student Network for several years and I met people from probably over 50 countries. I
have no idea, I never counted them.  Everyone in this circle of friends is proud of their mobility and my social media
feeds are covered with people flying to places or moving somewhere else. I got my girlfriend a “Cities Book” and we are
looking at cities such as Toronto, Sydney, Vienna, Berlin, London and Brussels for our future home. She’s from Naples
and I am from Cologne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have &lt;em&gt;two groups&lt;/em&gt; of friends. Those that are like us and those that are not. Some shiver at the idea of going to another
city or even country for more than a vacation. Others, those that have experienced an exchange (or two or three), aren’t
surprised the least bit about the fact that the two of us don’t know which continent we will live on next New Years Eve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all terribly proud of what we can do and for good reason. The amount of experiences we have is exhilarating. I
want to believe that we are also less likely to follow propaganda against other minorities or countries. I would never
attack another country and kill another human, solely because a politician (manager) of my &lt;em&gt;current, arbitrarily
defined organizational unit&lt;/em&gt; that we call countries doesn’t like another manager of another such unit. And those
entangled political situations such as those visible in the middle east right now are so wildly in-transparent that
again, I would never be convinced to pick up a rifle and shoot another person who, under different circumstances, I
might have enjoyed meeting in a little Jordanian restaurant in a city I decided to spend time in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobility and explicit pride and fostering of multinational and multi ethnic circles of friends therefore has many
benefits. My arrogant claim: If everyone had friends in many countries and if everyone had lived in a handful of them,
large-scale conflicts &lt;em&gt;caused by the reasons we see today&lt;/em&gt; would be far less likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dark-side&quot;&gt;The dark side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a dark side to all of this and I don’t think many of &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; see this side. If everyone is as mobile as we
are, then cities and regions have to cope with a completely different scale of population movement. 200 years ago
the large majority of people died within a small radius of where they were born. Surely, some individuals moved around almost
as freely as we do today. But those were a small number of elite academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s imagine everyone having the mobility I have described above. Moving around the country and the world several
times a lifetime, following the current stream of people and going by what the (socioeconomic) environment offers us. AI is the big hype right now and London seems
to be the place to be for that. All those that like AI therefore think about moving to London, if they are willing to jump
continent they will want to move to San Francisco or Shanghai. Similar patterns will be visible for robotics,
cloud technologies, genetics, etc. Any field of profession that largely relies on cognitive work and where network
effects support many people of the same field to live close together to collaborate will be susceptible to this kind of
pattern. The pattern is nothing new. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/taiwan-battles-a-brain-drain-as-china-aims-to-woo-young-talent-away/2018/04/13/338d096e-3940-11e8-af3c-2123715f78df_story.html?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.2f2b79e4f2fc&quot; title=&quot;Brain Drain&quot;&gt;Brain Drain&lt;/a&gt; has been discussed many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s look at the loser cities. It is largely accepted that the countryside has a massive brain drain and that many
people move to the cities. But what if your city doesn’t have a world-class university and if your local or national
government has been entangled in a few years of internal power struggles or just missed an opportunity to jump on the
 train for the next big thing? If you increase mobility &lt;em&gt;starting from the top&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. when education and mobility is
correlated, those that are left behind are less educated and lacking a competitive strength that is needed for economic
equality. Formerly, people moved &lt;em&gt;into the city&lt;/em&gt;, but now we move &lt;em&gt;to the best city&lt;/em&gt;. That causes system dynamics that
may lead to large populations without any ability to compete with other cities. Examples? Look at Detroit, look at Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_960/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg 960w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1280/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg 1280w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_1500/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-04-16/detroit.jpg 1500w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;cover for post&quot; width=&quot;1500&quot; height=&quot;974&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Photo in Detroit by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@j6flores&quot;&gt;Jorge Flores&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and people like me, those that take pride in their mobility, open mindedness and skill set, we are a major factor of
this problem. If we are not happy with our city and its investments in our field, we abandon it. And while we have every
right to do so, the ease with which we make that choice leads to unforeseen consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;detours-reveal-unexpected-insights&quot;&gt;Detours reveal unexpected insights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to paint you a picture of what I have seen in the city of Naples over the last 6 months. I started my trip
down here by reading John Hoopers &lt;strong&gt;The Italians&lt;/strong&gt; and my experiences often mirror his (with some risk of confirmation
bias baked in).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This city, which has been titled as the &lt;em&gt;“oldest continously inhabited city in the world”&lt;/em&gt;  has many charms but one
problem: It’s stagnating and there seems no way out. The city with the longest history has a future problem.  Italy has
historically been described as divided into the agricultural south and the service oriented and industrialized north.
Naples suffers massive public transport issues, it’s universities don’t receive funding because the region has no money
and, intuitively, it has an aging infrastructure. Stadiums, churches and streets are crumbling, and the society is
locked in a weird conflict between extreme local pride and embarrassment for its current state. There is little to no
English proficiency here which seems to be due to aged teaching methodologies being applied all over its schools. People
are strangely unaware of what happens in the world. Italians have been described as quiet uninterested in foreign news
stories, with national and local news dominating the air-time. They watch a lot of TV, but every show is translated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple built a Developer Academy in Naples, although it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/2016/01/25/apples-new-ios-center-naples-raises-eyebrows/79320404/&quot;&gt;has been
suggested&lt;/a&gt; to
maybe have something to do with them owing a few hundred million in taxes to the Italians. Other than this though, I was
&lt;em&gt;to this day&lt;/em&gt; not able to find a group of people that talk about software engineering in Naples. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/find/events/tech/?allMeetups=false&amp;amp;radius=50&amp;amp;userFreeform=Naples%2C+Italy&amp;amp;mcId=c1022167&amp;amp;mcName=Napoli%2C+IT&quot;&gt;meetup calendar&lt;/a&gt;
is empty, and people really just don’t seem to care. Everyone has a smartphone but digital is something that comes from
somewhere else. Naples makes good cheese, good Pizza, good &amp;lt;insert-food-here&amp;gt;. They will never stop to stress this.
But this does not generate enough wealth for some 3 Million people. So, Italy in general and the south especially sees
strong migration from highly skilled people. “Milan is different”, “Milan has everything”, “I’ll go to Milan”. Many of
the people I talk to say Milan is the place to be. They were educated here, raised here and they leave their parents and
grandparents behind while going up north to find a future. Meanwhile, it stands to reason what is worse: Loosing all
your youth to other parts of the world or not having enough funding to push &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; waiting times for much-needed public transport below 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have no system in place to help struggling cities! Some countries have systems in place to help individuals to
receive social welfare checks but this is no solution… If we increase our mobility more and more, we will have
stronger system dynamics, leading to stronger concentrations of winners in some places and losers in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-trade-players&quot;&gt;Let’s trade players&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to continue the increasing mobility of people, something that I believe is just as much a right as speech or
choice of friends, we need to be ready for an ever increasing difference between cities ability to compete with each
other. There will be cities that are &lt;em&gt;tech X cities&lt;/em&gt; while others will see almost nothing of this sector. Every city for
itself must try to foster a network of people for new fields but if that fails and the new field is the source for a
large part of global economic growth, adequate balancing mechanisms needs to be in place as to not punish those people
who have worked in fields that now see a decline in demand. It is not fair for people in Detroit to be abandoned after
having provided the US with their most iconic symbol of freedom for decades. London wasn’t home to all its bankers and
AI specialists and San Francisco did not give birth to all of its software engineering talent. Yet they benefit greatly
from those people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There might be several models that could alleviate these differences: Financial support for under performing cities
similar to schemes on national levels  are the most intuitive and classical approach, although cutting out the middleman
of the nation state might be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up with something different that I believe might be worth
discussing. Oddly enough, I just watched my first football match in a stadium last weekend. Football players switch their
club by being traded. They get paid by their club but clubs can purchase players from each other. There is an obviously
large mobility of players between clubs but there is also a similar &lt;em&gt;two groups&lt;/em&gt; kind of structure. Some never change,
some are very mobile. What if, just as with players, regions or cities are embedded in a similar system? If a PhD
student of neuroscience who has been educated well and prepared for the future by a city leaves said city the day after
her graduation, that city has just lost a large investment. And because of the flowing of human capital between regions,
some regions have a larger loss than others who benefit greatly from the investment of others. But if each time a person
transfers, a payment is transferred in exchange, the region that looses said person gains financial support to
strengthen its position in a field that it might benefit from in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this puts a price tag on every person who moves from place to place. Is this morally sound? To be honest, I have no
idea. I am happy to hear arguments against this concept. The value would basically balance the persons future potential
for value creation against the potential for cost inducement. Some might be worth more and some might be worth less.
Obviously, it shouldn’t be possible to block people from moving because of their potential future costs (at least not
more than is done today though borders, walls and immigration controls). It would however allow every region to benefit
from bright minds that are originating from within its population, even if they end up moving to a place where all the
others like them hang out at. It would give communities like Naples the financial freedom to invest into its strengths
or to foster new strengths. It could create a tech community that doesn’t rely on a brand name from Cupertino. It could
finally start having a subway line that runs past 10pm or reopen one of its largest churches which has been abandoned
for over 20 years because no one has the money to clean it up. Or it could finally buy its Universities some computers
so the librarians don’t need to manage everything with pen and paper anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-path-to-follow&quot;&gt;A path to follow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a bright kid from the Greek Island Kreta turns out to have strong talent in the field of robotics, it will likely
want to move to a place where its skills can be fostered. A lot of money lies in this field, surely more than in the
production and sales of tomatoes and olive oil. This kid receives basic education and decides to move to Zurich when it
turns 19. Zurich now educates it in the field and 4 years later it moves to Wolfsburg in Germany where it works for
Volkswagen and generates millions in profit through advancements in production technology. How does Kreta benefit from
this potential? Not at all. But if each time the person moved, a payment was performed between the regions, Kreta would
have received compensation for the education and raising of said person and Zurich receives payment for its higher
education investments. Even better, Kreta has an incentive to invest into its youth, because they have the largest
potential to be both come up with new ideas that help the local region or, if they choose to leave, result in larger
positive payment transfers. Now, this money can be invested in ensuring the local population remains pleased with the offers
and the life quality of the region and it might (and should) even be invested to improve the regions attractiveness for
its strengths, such as tourism, retreat opportunities or as a retirement destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-things-breaking-things&quot;&gt;Changing things, breaking things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is fresh, raw and unchallenged. Break it, tell me why its wrong and let’s see if what comes out might be a
compromise that is worth pursuing. I would be happy to hear if people agree and why as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is getting smaller in many ways. People like to reference the coach, train, car and plane as symbols to show
how small the world is nowadays. But everyday life still happens in one city. Sure we travel around the world for
vacation (although there are also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2010/apr/06/aviation-q-and-a&quot; title=&quot;Aviation CO2 impact&quot;&gt;arguments against that&lt;/a&gt;), but regular days happen in our cities and if
our cities are systematically winning or loosing, that is something we need to compensate for. It’s easy for a software engineer like me to bitch about all the things that are wrong about my current city here in Italy. But then, I shouldn’t forget, most people here did not choose their city to have these problems. People didn’t decide to wait 30 minutes for their trains every morning. They didn’t decide to walk along the tracks because the train broke down &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want our mobility and our pride, we might have to put a price tag on some things. So that those parts of the world
that are being robbed of their bright minds get the means to ensure that this is not a permanent disparity. We trade
goods and services, maybe it’s time we also trade humans. Oh that sounds so wrong. Not like the old days, please! But you get the idea!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="Erasmus," /><category term="society," /><category term="mobility" /><summary type="html">Looking at what happens when young professionals can move around the world as they please and at the places they leave behind</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turning your Linux computer into a screencast station for pareto principle level professionality</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/04/15/Turning_your_Linux_computer_into_a_screencast_station_for_pareto_principle_level_professionality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turning your Linux computer into a screencast station for pareto principle level professionality" /><published>2018-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/04/15/Turning_your_Linux_computer_into_a_screencast_station_for_pareto_principle_level_professionality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/04/15/Turning_your_Linux_computer_into_a_screencast_station_for_pareto_principle_level_professionality.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(See video tour at the bottom of the post or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WVnf_AXz3S0&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recently decided to record some of my coding sessions and put them on the internet. Why? Well, firstly it’s a good way to show what I can (and can’t) do. If I apply somewhere for a Data Scientist or Software Engineering position I can show what’s to expect from me. But of course it also serves the purpose of focus, as you tend to think your actions through when you are &lt;em&gt;on record&lt;/em&gt;. So while recording yourself, you tend to explain exactly what you do and that helps in itself to generate better results (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging&quot;&gt;ruber duck debugging&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many YouTube personalities have crazy incomes and equally crazy equipment. Others (the long tail of the distribution) have barely any income and most of them tend to just do a quick tutorial or tips and tricks video with their webcam. Both worlds have advantages and disadvantages: The top tier streamers are a goal not worth aiming for. If you’re rational you don’t expect to become the 0.01%, especially not by doing tutorials on Linux and AI like me. But you can still try and get some quality into your videos to make them more enjoyable. So here are three core steps for doing so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-get-a-good-microphone&quot;&gt;1. Get a good microphone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t necessarily mean expensive. I just mean good. I mean better than your laptop microphone and I mean better than your phones. I got myself the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aukey.com/products/usb-condenser-microphone-mi-u1&quot;&gt;Aukey MI-U1&lt;/a&gt; which ran me around €60 and it feels and sounds solid. It’s a USB microphone so no connecting to studio equipment but for me it’s perfect. It’s a condenser and offers several controls. But I won’t repeat the specs page, here is what you should aim for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adjustable output on mic → makes it easy to adjust volume without fiddling with system settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Lowcut filter? Do it in the Software. -10dB, sure nice but again, software. Unless you tend to really yell a lot. If your grandpa still has an old microphone in his office, ask him if you can take it. Get an adaptor for the thing and plug it into your Mic input. It’s probably even better, microphones have been good for the last 40 years, they’ve just gotten a lot cheaper since China happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-add-a-microphone-arm-for-added-space&quot;&gt;2. Add a microphone arm for added space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you take the standard microphone setup, it’s directly in front of you and you’ve got a cable running under your arm behind the keyboard and down the back. That’s both annoying and not ideal because that way the mic is very close to the keyboard. With a microphone arm, it’s much more variable to position and it’s about €16 to buy one of those. Plus the whole thing starts to feel really professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/5000/1*BhXoWEBY8QwM61K7mzkZ2g.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;entry condenser mic with pop protection&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;entry condenser mic with pop protection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-get-a-tripod-for-your-camera-phone&quot;&gt;3. Get a tripod for your camera phone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come on, everyone has a smartphone. They’ve got great cameras. Use it! If you’re an iPhone owner, sorry. I wouldn’t know how to stream the cam recordings directly to the computer screen. But maybe you have a DSLR or even an old pocket camera lying around. Both will work as well but you can’t include the video stream directly inside the screen recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Android however, we have a nifty little app called &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ronakpatel1311.camerastreamer&quot;&gt;Camera Stream Wifi&lt;/a&gt;. It accesses your phones camera and creates a little http server that you can navigate to in your browser. The result is a nice camera feed. Wrap that with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/nativefier&quot;&gt;nativefier&lt;/a&gt; and you’ve got yourself a desktop app that uses your phones camera as a video source. I’ve got my window set to always on top, always visible so when I switch among desktops, I’m always in the bottom right corner of the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attached my camera to the lamp next to my desk. The tripod can wrap around the pole neatly and the phone is not rocked by any movements of the desk which helps with the video quality. Probably around €10–15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/5000/1*xfC_XhDg6O3znrTZcnPLXA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;simple tripod with wrapping arms&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;simple tripod with wrapping arms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait you said 3 steps. Yes, well you can order all three things on Amazon right? That’s 1 step ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 2: Get some software. I use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;**Audacity for audio editing: **Removing noise, increasing the bass a bit for a fuller sounding voice (which can compensate for not being really close to the mic, which leads to loss of low hertz frequencies) and normalizing the whole track to -2dB. You can also run the whole thing in one “Chain” and probably that will even work from the terminal. So maybe it’s all scriptable so you’d only have to run a shell script on your file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SimpleScreenRecorder:&lt;/strong&gt; To record the screen I use this. It allows for setting of a hotkey so I can quickly start and pause the recording. The whole thing is created as a single file or split at each pause, you can choose. There are surely more advanced versions but I like it. Simple, light, self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ffmpeg:&lt;/strong&gt; I let SimpleScreenRecorder record the audio. That way it pauses both audio and video when I pause. I don’t intend to cut my video after the fact but just do them in one go with occasional pauses. ffmpeg allows to quickly split audio from video, edit it in audacity and merge them again&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg -i video.mp4 -c copy -an video_out.mp4 audio_out.mp3
#edit in audacity
ffmpeg -i video_out.mp4 -i audio_edited.mp3 -c copy upload.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the lazy here is the apt-get for the tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install simplescreenrecorder audacity
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configure-simplescreenrecorder&quot;&gt;Configure SimpleScreenRecorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing works straight out of the box. But I like less FPS. I’m doing coding, &lt;strong&gt;most of the screen doesn’t move so there is no need for high FPS&lt;/strong&gt;. Sure, if you do 3D things or anything where movement is a key factor, don’t go so low. I’m just trying to save bandwidth both on my upload and on the people that stream this stuff on their phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*g0XoYBHNayPRcKAYPk9-Aw.png&quot; alt=&quot;10 fps are enough for screencasts I believe. Jack them up to 30 or 60 if you feel like it&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;10 fps are enough for screencasts I believe. Jack them up to 30 or 60 if you feel like it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mac-and-windows&quot;&gt;Mac and Windows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Mac you can just use Quicktime Player to do screen recordings. But there are also other alternatives out there, free and paid. On Windows I have no clue, I haven’t touched those in almost 10 years now. A quick search brought up &lt;a href=&quot;https://getsharex.com/&quot;&gt;sharex&lt;/a&gt; which looks and sounds legit. Give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-a-short-story-and-record&quot;&gt;Prepare a short story and record&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a notebook, write down your path on a piece of paper and go with that. A small script, however short it is helps to keep the whole story as it’s supposed to be. My first few recordings are completely free and I just uploaded one of them, because I was too embarrassed to upload the rest. Sure you can just record yourself do whatever but if you try to create a short video that teaches people something as efficiently as possible instead of just showing what you do, then make a script. After that, you’re good to go&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WVnf_AXz3S0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="technology," /><category term="linux," /><category term="screencast," /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">A tour of my linux screencast setup to exhibit how to quickly turn a computer into a screencast studio for high quality online screencasts</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Enabling Tensorboard to see what’s happening during training of an LSTM on Keras using a Timeseries Generator</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/30/Enabling_Tensorboard_when_training_an_LSTM_on_Keras_using_a_TimeseriesGenerator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enabling Tensorboard to see what's happening during training of an LSTM on Keras using a Timeseries Generator" /><published>2018-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/30/Enabling_Tensorboard_when_training_an_LSTM_on_Keras_using_a_TimeseriesGenerator</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/30/Enabling_Tensorboard_when_training_an_LSTM_on_Keras_using_a_TimeseriesGenerator.html">&lt;p&gt;Learning neural networks is still very messy, so without tools such as tensorboard, it would be really hard to really
comprehend what is happening. Unfortunately, it’s not super easy to get tensorboard working out-of-the-box with Keras
when training certain structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When running an LSTM learning algorithm on large datasets, it is sometimes needed to generate the sequences on the fly
and feed the data that is used to learn the algorithms in several steps. If the size of the data is large but the series
for each logical unit is small however, it is often not possible to run several epochs on the whole set but rather run
single epochs on each smaller unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my specific case I was analyzing some 3GB of sequential forecast data and its corresponding realized data values. To
learn from historical data, it is necessary to let the LSTM see anything from up to 7 days before the current reading.
That equates to each sequence being equal to about &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;24 * 7&lt;/script&gt; the size of the original data. That is clearly too much
to generate ahead of time and then just feed to the CPU from memory. So a different approach is needed. Because the
whole dataset cannot be fed to the LSTM directly however, I am using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;model.fit_generator&lt;/code&gt; API of Keras. This allows
me to pass a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Sequence&lt;/code&gt; object that generates Sequences from an underlying data array on the fly. This API doesn’t
support the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;validation_split&lt;/code&gt; flag, which requires me to pass a separate generator to the API for its validation steps.
However, this is not supported by Tensorflow (no generators allowed), which requires me to create a separate Tuple of
(X,Y) values that is in-memory and that can be used for validation. Since this doesn’t need to be so large, it fits into
memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My overall learning structure sort of looks as such&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;run_full_learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# iterate over games (holding customer lists)
&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;g_number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;game&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;enumerate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;preprocessing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GamesIterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# iterating over customers in game
&lt;/span&gt;		&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# sequences is [generator, validation_set]
&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sequences&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;preprocessing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CustomerIterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;game&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;game&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit_with_generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mdl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sequences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sequences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mdl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;save_weights&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;data/consume/game{}.HDF5&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;g_number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I train my model on every customer sequence which is some 2000 timesteps long and which has 17 features per timestep.
Every game holds about 200 customers and I have about 100 games. After training on every customer, tensorboard gets to
validate and calculate the loss after each epoch is done (and each epoch is one customer set being completed). The exact
train call of Keras is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;model.fit_generator(train_generator,
                    steps_per_epoch=None,  #a generator size (aka one customer) is an epoch
                    epochs=1,
                    verbose=2,  #progress bar, 2 = line per epoch
                    callbacks=callbacks,
                    validation_data=validation_set,
                    #validation_steps=None,
                    class_weight=None,
                    max_queue_size=10,
                    workers=8,
                    use_multiprocessing=True,
                    shuffle=True,
                    initial_epoch=0)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To generate the validation set, I first used the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;util.TimeseriesGenerator&lt;/code&gt; to generate the sequences. But since I&lt;br /&gt;
don’t actually want to feed a generator to tensorflow, I instead converted it back into an array that I can give to
Keras. This way, Tensorboard is happy about the fact that it is not receiving a generator and I am happy because I get
visual feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;	def generate_batches_for_customer(data, targets):
    	&quot;&quot;&quot;[keras docs](https://keras.io/preprocessing/sequence/#timeseriesgenerator)&quot;&quot;&quot;
    	return TimeseriesGenerator(data,
        	                       targets,
        	                       length=SEQUENCE_LENGTH,
        	                       sampling_rate=SAMPLING_RATE,
        	                       batch_size=BATCH_SIZE)
#...

     make_sequences(self, cutofa, data, targets):
        &quot;&quot;&quot;given a cutoff and two data arrays, generate Sequences from it (one before cutoff one after&quot;&quot;&quot;
        training_sequence   = generate_batches_for_customer(np.array(data[:-cutoff]), np.array(targets[:-cutoff]))
        validation_sequence = generate_batches_for_customer(np.array(data[-cutoff:]), np.array(targets[-cutoff:]))
        return training_sequence, validation_sequence

    def get_next_pair(self):
        &quot;&quot;&quot;pops the first of both arrays out and returns it&quot;&quot;&quot;
        data    = self.data_customers.pop(0)
        targets = self.targets_customers.pop(0)
        return data, targets

    def convert_sequence_to_set(self, sequence: Sequence):
        #this is a set of tuples. We need a tuple of sets...
        x = []
        y = []
        for i in range(sequence.length):
            batch = sequence[i]
            x.extend(batch[0])
            y.extend(batch[1])
        return np.array(x), np.array(y)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to sum it up, it is possible to get Tensorboard going with util.Sequence from a TimeseriesGenerators, but it’s a
little messy as we first make a Sequence object and then drain it of all sequences to pass directly to the train method.
I guess a future API update will allow Sequence objects also when using a Tensorboard callback but for now this will do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="keras," /><category term="tensorflow," /><category term="tensorboard," /><category term="lstm," /><category term="machine" /><category term="learning," /><category term="data" /><category term="science," /><summary type="html">Learning neural networks is still very messy, so without tools such as tensorboard, it would be really hard to really comprehend what is happening. Unfortunately, it’s not super easy to get tensorboard working out-of-the-box with Keras when training certain structures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Want to do</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/22/Want_to_do.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Want to do" /><published>2018-03-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/22/Want_to_do</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/22/Want_to_do.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some projects that I want to do when I find the time for them. They are ideas for possible online businesses,
simple websites, libraries or what have you. If you have time to do it, feel free to do so if you contribute me as an
ideaist and let me know how it goes. They are not sorted in any particular order although that might change at some
point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-collection-of-must-have-databases--books--articles-for-a-potential-internet-shutdown&quot;&gt;A collection of “must have” databases / books / articles for a potential internet shutdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our society is pretty digital. But it’s also pretty dependent on this tech. What if that is not available anymore? What
if it just all stops working? I want an offline version of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maps (openstreetmaps) &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Downloading_data&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Database_download&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a collection of ebooks for survival, nature, building things etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most important pieces of knowledge as epub&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whatever else may be useful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole thing should fit on an external hard drive, be self contained (i.e. contain all the libraries needed to make
it run on contemporary windows / linux system hardware). I am thinking, ideally this would be a life bootable linux
system that has the wikipedia and openstreetmaps databases running inside of it as well as all the files on a readable
partition. That + a few ebook readers may allow for very low-power knowledge distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keyboard-typing-audio-filter-for-microphones&quot;&gt;Keyboard typing audio filter for microphones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Has been sort of been made obsolote by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2018/04/google-works-out-a-fascinating-slightly-scary-way-for-ai-to-isolate-voices-in-a-crowd/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural Networks are really good at pattern recognition. Adversarial neural networks are really good at creating fake
images that look almost real. That is because the first NN is trained to recognize images while the second one is
trained to fool the first one. So here is my idea: If you have a keylogger that logs the time of each keystroke down to
the millisecond, as well as a stream of audio of recording, you could train a neural network that recognizes these
keystrokes and then a second one that gets the original audio stream and needs to manipulate the stream so as to fool
the first one (so that the first one doesn’t recognize the keystrokes anymore) while keeping the stream as untouched as
possible. Hence the second one will get a reward for the first one not being able to recognize strokes while also
getting less reward the more the original stream is changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;telegram-bot-to-control-some-home-activities&quot;&gt;Telegram Bot to control some home activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/pascalwhoopbutler&quot;&gt;In the works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bot that runs on the Pi at home could easily be written to offer several commands to me. I could have a folder with
python or bash scripts that each holds a named script. Then the bot could offer me to remotely trigger those scripts via
telegram messages. This would be less technical than having to SSH into the machine and can also avoid a lot of firewall
issues. But the bot needs to have some authentication scheme as anyone can write my bot. I used to have this for my
lights at home because my roomates had old phones and our lights were controlled by Apples Homekit (using a bridge on a
Pi to the 433mhz plugs). That asked for a secret password before you could do anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whentomove&quot;&gt;WhenToMove&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A website that takes two locations and then tells you the times of the year when one or the other has more dailight
hours, less rain etc. I live in Naples right now, where it’s warmer than in Germany but rainier until end of April. You
could give a set of weights for different categories (rain, sunshine, daylight, …) and the app would give you
recommended moving dates in the year. A lot of people (who can afford it) in Europe live somewhere in the south during the winter and up
north in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cms-service-based-on-github-and-jekyll&quot;&gt;CMS service based on GitHub and Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning this website pattern into something that can be served online as a service for small scale teams. I have this
website without any costs aside from the domain name. GitHub is my CMS, Google Firebase hosts it and creates SSL certs.
Because the code is public, I can use CircleCI to build on commit and I use Cloudinary to ensure efficient images are
served using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nhoizey.github.io/jekyll-cloudinary/&quot;&gt;jekyll plugin&lt;/a&gt;. The only problem is that beginners will
not be able to cope with GitHub and especially the decentral nature of Git. A web interface for writing posts that has
some form of Authentication should be enough to cover most people while keeping one person in the team who needs to
understand jekyll, HTML/CSS and Git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chatgroups-based-on-location-closeness&quot;&gt;Chatgroups based on location closeness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, there are large groups of people meeting that don’t share a phone number and that need to stay in touch for a few
days. Such groups could be tours with guides, student trips, group vacations, city competitions etc. A chat app that
allows you to quickly create a chatroom that anyone that is closeby can join would help people to share their activities
without the need to exchange phone numbers with everyone. The process would look as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Group leader opens a room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone in the vicinity is asked to join&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone joined receives a link that can be used to join later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app could also have some other cool features such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peer to peer based image sharing&lt;/strong&gt;: Often, groups go to parties together and they want to share their pics. Who wants
a WhatsApp compressed pic though… no one likes bad quality pics. So a feature could be to share all images taken in
a specified period by everyone with everyone else. So we go out with friends? All pics between 10pm and 4am are shared
with the group once the phones get back to WiFi. With 5G this could take off even more because phones could share
directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-deletion-script&quot;&gt;Facebook deletion script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook really doesn’t offer much other than:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a list of friends&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;birthdays&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;groups for buying, sharing, gifting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a script that runs on the lightweight activity log on &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.facebook.com/&quot;&gt;m.facebook.com&lt;/a&gt; and deletes all old posts would be a nice thing. The “Delete” buttons don’t trigger any “are you sure” dialogs and offer a URL that can be used to delete things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a
lref=&quot;/allactivity/removecontent/?profile_id=1118218499&amp;amp;amp;action=remove_comment&amp;amp;amp;timeline_token=1400914419%3A1076331159073387%3A1%3B1501034974%3A1120930962&amp;amp;amp;ent_identifier=S%3A_I2420210499%3A1876231159373387%3A1&amp;amp;amp;ext=1521963589&amp;amp;amp;hash=AeRUZ7R8VsSm9FEN&quot;
class=&quot;cy&quot;&amp;gt;Delete&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can then be asynchronously called and all sorts of stuff from the past can be deleted. Who needs to keep posts
from 2012 around anyways?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="todo" /><summary type="html">A WIP list on things I wanna do or build that are tech related.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting to screencast about my thesis and machine learning</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/21/Starting_to_screencast_about_my_thesis_and_machine_learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting to screencast about my thesis and machine learning" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/21/Starting_to_screencast_about_my_thesis_and_machine_learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/03/21/Starting_to_screencast_about_my_thesis_and_machine_learning.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An updated version of this post is available &lt;a href=&quot;/technology/2018/04/15/Turning_your_Linux_computer_into_a_screencast_station_for_pareto_principle_level_professionality.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have posted my first video on YouTube about how to do screencasts on Linux with free tools and without having to
invest heavily into hardware. I only added a microphone to the mix but even that I had lying around already for
recording music. It’s not ideal for screencasts because it is made to record stereo full room sound but it’s a good
start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CQzPwWBdswI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay;
encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the basic things you need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good mic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solid Wifi &amp;amp; Upload&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smartphone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decent PC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean background (unlike me)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jack Audio for Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SimpleScreenRecorder for Linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use your phone as a webcam, get a tripod or some books and download 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ronakpatel1311.camerastreamer&quot;&gt;this app&lt;/a&gt; and connect to it via the
browser. Optionally install &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;node&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; then run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install -g nativefier&lt;/code&gt; to then run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nativefier -i ~/Desktop/cam.png -n PhoneCam --inject /home/pascalwhoop/Desktop/custom_css_cam.css  --width 1280 --height
720 http://192.168.1.203:8080/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know how the tools work out for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="technology,blog,screencast,linux" /><summary type="html">I am starting to upload screencasts about my developments of the agent for my thesis. This is the initial video</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should I reinvent the weather?</title><link href="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/02/12/Should_I_reinvent_the_weather_.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should I reinvent the weather?" /><published>2018-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/02/12/Should_I_reinvent_the_weather_</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pascalbrokmeier.de/technology/2018/02/12/Should_I_reinvent_the_weather_.html">&lt;p&gt;In my journey towards a powertac agent I discovered the complexity behind the weather server and thought about adapting it to make it easily deployable in a container. Once it’s in a container, other teams could quickly start up an instance of their own without many dependencies (really just docker). But then I realized some oddities with the way it is set up. To generate an xml file (or alternatively serve them via REST), a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python - mysql - python - mysql - java - python&lt;/code&gt; chain is set up. And to make it worse, all mysql commands are non-optimized atomic requests inside of loops in python. No bulking, no parallel processing etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s think about this. We are pulling 18 years of forecast data from the servers. That’s about 150k datapoints, which makes sense as we have 18 years with 24h per day. But how many points are we importing into the database?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;START_DATE = &quot;20090101&quot; # YYYYMMDD of earliest report
END_DATE = &quot;20111231&quot; # YYYYMMDD of last report
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so 3 years, aka 26298 datapoints. Now for each hour of these 3 years
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/powertac/powertac-weather-server/blob/master/scripts/create_forecast_data.py&quot;&gt;this script&lt;/a&gt; generates 24 forecasts for the upcoming 24 hours. Let’s do the math here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;3 \times 365 \times 24 \times 24 = 630720&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all good and well though. The problem really lies in the way the code is structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-implementation-creating-deltas&quot;&gt;Current implementation: Creating Deltas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first look at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;create_forecast_deltas.py&lt;/code&gt; file (with some added inline comments by me):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#imports ...

OUT_FILE = &quot;deltas.txt&quot;
MAX_ERROR = 0.0001
TOTAL = 1000000 # &amp;lt;-- this one. 1Mio! it's the counter of a loop later
DELTAS = [
    0.5161445829244465,
    0.4997949220914800,
    #... len(DELTAS) = 24

]
TARGETS = [
    0.5161290323,
    1.6221198157
    #... len(TARGETS) = 24
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-08/targets.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-08/targets.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_397/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-08/targets.png 397w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;397&quot; height=&quot;271&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#main moved above for ease of top-down readability.
def main():
    errors = [0.0] * len(TARGETS)
    current = 0

    with open(OUT_FILE, 'w') as f:
        f.write(&quot;&quot;)

    #this loop gets iterated over 24 times (len(TARGETS) break below)
    while True:
        #current = 0, 1, 2, 3, ...
        error = loop(current)

        #difference between MSE and target MSE (i.e. MSE is supposed to increase over 24h predicition period)
        diff = error - TARGETS[current]
        change = 1 - max(MAX_ERROR, abs(diff) / 5)

        #next big block: comparing MSE to targets. If not fitting, iterating millions of times AGAIN.
        print current, DELTAS[current], change
        print error, TARGETS[current]
        print (&quot;%.6f&quot; % diff),
        if diff &amp;gt; MAX_ERROR:
            print &quot;diff larger&quot;
            DELTAS[current] = DELTAS[current] * change
        elif diff &amp;lt; -MAX_ERROR:
            print &quot;diff smaller&quot;
            DELTAS[current] = DELTAS[current] / change
        else:   
            print &quot;diff OK&quot;
            with open(OUT_FILE, 'a') as f:
                f.write(&quot;%d %.16f\n&quot; % (current, DELTAS[current]))
            errors[current] = error
            current += 1

        if current &amp;gt;= len(TARGETS):
            break

    print
    print len(errors), len(DELTAS)
    print
    print errors
    print
    print DELTAS
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above block is not at all understandable to me. It seems as if the code is trying to achieve a DELTAS list that is &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; to a function resembling the derivative of the TARGETS (which are a log function) without being exact. Why this wasn’t just performed by taking 24 values of a log function and adding some noise to them, I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next function shows how a loop iterating over our &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TOTAL&lt;/code&gt; range (1 Mio.) and then iterating over current+1 which means 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 … iterations for each subsequent &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;loop(current)&lt;/code&gt; call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sum_{i=1}^{25}{i} * 1{.}000{.}000 = 300{.}000{.}000 \text{iterations}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def loop(current):
    forecasts = []

    #1Mio times
    for _ in range(TOTAL):
        tau = 0
        temp = []
        for i in range(current+1):
            tau = tau + random.gauss(0, DELTAS[i])
            temp.append(tau)
        forecasts.append(temp)

    error = 0.0
    #mean squared error
    for forecast in forecasts:
        error += forecast[current] ** 2
    error = math.sqrt(error / len(forecasts))

    return error

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sample output of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;create_forecast_deltas.py&lt;/code&gt; script&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0 0.516144582924 0.9999
0.515986943719 0.5161290323
-0.000142 diff smaller

0 0.516196202545 0.9999
0.516100208138 0.5161290323
-0.000029 diff OK

1 0.499794922091 0.999807649737
0.717932257886 0.7188940092
-0.000962 diff smaller

1 0.499891076271 0.9999
0.719294262397 0.7188940092
0.000400 diff larger

1 0.499841087164 0.999847349058
0.718130754489 0.7188940092
-0.000763 diff smaller

1 0.499917400026 0.9999
0.718902314128 0.7188940092
0.000008 diff OK

2 0.488890089098 0.99970675704
0.868349453399 0.8698156682
-0.001466 diff smaller

2 0.489033494728 0.999823374688
0.868932541638 0.8698156682
-0.000883 diff smaller

2 0.48911988568 0.999660646651
0.868118901454 0.8698156682
-0.001697 diff smaller

2 0.489285926498 0.9999
0.87002069015 0.8698156682
0.000205 diff larger

2 0.489236997906 0.999709463393
0.868362985166 0.8698156682
-0.001453 diff smaller

2 0.489379180472 0.999886141672
0.869246376561 0.8698156682
-0.000569 diff smaller

2 0.489434906712 0.999877799512
0.869204665758 0.8698156682
-0.000611 diff smaller

2 0.489494723206 0.999885588796
0.869243612179 0.8698156682
-0.000572 diff smaller

2 0.489550733295 0.999866629795
0.869148817175 0.8698156682
-0.000667 diff smaller

2 0.489616033486 0.999759522789
0.871018054255 0.8698156682
0.001202 diff larger

2 0.489498291988 0.999856598225
0.869098659324 0.8698156682
-0.000717 diff smaller

2 0.489568496979 0.9999
0.869614687695 0.8698156682
-0.000201 diff smaller
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it seems this is all just used to generate some deltas that are close, but not on-point to the delta between each discrete step of two adjacent log function values. The purpose is that in the next script, these deltas get used to create an increasingly uncertain weather forecast for the next 24h (game horizon in powertac) without going off-the-charts. I will ask my supervisor what exactly the motivation behind those deltas is but for now, let’s assume they are given (as they are in the forecast generation scripts anyways)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-implementation-creating-forecast-data&quot;&gt;Current implementation: Creating Forecast Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/powertac/powertac-weather-server/blob/master/scripts/create_forecast_data.py&quot;&gt;create_forecast_data.py&lt;/a&gt;
works as follows (pseudo-code)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#[temp,speed,dir,cloud]
taus = np.zeros((4,24)) #4x24 matrix
origin = date(&quot;20090101&quot;)

while origin &amp;lt; end_date: #sequential

    weather = get_48h_weather() #48 sql queries in here
    taus = np.zeros((4,24))

    # make deviations
    for i in range(24):
        taus = taus[:,i-1] + np.random.normal(0, DELTAS[i],4) #shortened by me

    for i in range(24): #seq again
        weather_date = origin + hours(1)
        for j in range(24): #24^2*len(dates) seq iterations
            forecast_date = weather_date + hours(j+1)

            fc = (weather[forecast_date] + [2,1,10,0.1])*taus
            #fixing fcs to keep them in bounds (according to previous code)
            fc[1] = max(min(fc[1],19),0) #wind e [0,19]
            fc[2] = int((fc[2]) % 360)   #direction 360 deg
            fc[3] = max(min(cloud,1),0)  #cloud cover e [0,1]

            #insert into db ...

        #db commit
    origin += hours(1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is a condensed pseudo version, but the process is the same&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iterate over all days
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;iterate over each hour
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;generate 24h of forecast data
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;insert each forecast into database&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. That’s 630720 insert operations. No wonder, this is slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weatherbug&quot;&gt;Weatherbug?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather taus are actually reused. The forecast at 00:00 for 24:00 uses the same error as the forecast at 24:00 for 24:00+1(day). So A smart client could take the forecast for 24:00 at 00:00 and compare it with the actual values of 24:00 to then derive the taus for the 24h forecast of the next day. Any following forecast can then be error corrected and therefore is on-spot. In my eyes this is a flaw in the simulation. I contacted the team regarding this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;python-only-rewrite-zip--xml&quot;&gt;Python only rewrite zip &amp;gt; xml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I just want xml in the end, I’ll skip the whole DB round-trip and &lt;!-- TODO ???--&gt; vectorize some operations while we’re at it. The basic concept could be this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create method for generating 24 forecasts for each timeslot i based on [i+1:i+25] items in the list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;apply method on all elements either in sequence or to really pump up the speed in parallel (or even on GPU)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new implementation can download all data for 2000-today from the server, extract it and turn 3 years of weather reports into 3 years worth of forecast data based on the forecast generation approach in under a minute. That’s a LOT better than before. Why? Well it’s all in-memory and doesn’t do any I/O ops. The forecasts seem alright, as the graphic below shows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-12/simulations.png&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_320/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-12/simulations.png 320w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_640/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-12/simulations.png 640w, https://res.cloudinary.com/pascal-brokmeier/image/fetch/c_limit,f_auto,q_auto,w_800/http://pascalbrokmeier.de/images/posts/2018-02-12/simulations.png 800w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 50rem) 100rem, 90vw&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All forecasts are along the lines of the actual weather but with some error up and down the spectrum, with the errors getting bigger as time progresses. This algorithm is directly taken from the previous implementation so it’s not my work. But it seems to provide a decent forecast with some logarithmic error distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bottom-line&quot;&gt;Bottom line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new implementation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pascalwhoop/powertac-weather-python-v2&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. It is likely though that I will rewrite most of it again. I talked to John, the “father” of powertac and he told me he’s crawling most data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aerisweather.com/&quot;&gt;aeris&lt;/a&gt; and generating a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.umn.edu/~jcollins/weather_records.json&quot;&gt;json file&lt;/a&gt; from it. But he also expressed interest in me taking on the weather server. It seems so as if it would be welcomed if I make aweather-server that can generate this on a regular basis. I could therefore use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://darksky.net/dev/docs#api-request-types&quot;&gt;darksky.net api&lt;/a&gt; and generate data by polling their API (1000x a day is free). If I poll their API on a cloud machine once every hour for say 40 cities, I can stay under 1000 requests a day and collect enough data to supply the community with solid weather simulation data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pascal Brokmeier</name></author><category term="technology," /><category term="powertac," /><category term="thesis" /><summary type="html">In my journey towards a powertac agent I discovered the complexity behind the weather server and thought about adapting it to make it easily deployable in a container. Once it's in a container, other teams could quickly start up an instance of their own without many dependencies (really just docker). But then I realized some oddities with the way ...</summary></entry></feed>